Finding Aid for Computer-Aided Engineering Network (University of Michigan) records, 1983-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Computer-Aided Engineering Network (University of Michigan) records 1983-2008 1986-2005
University of Michigan. Computer-Aided Engineering Network.
2011123 BIU 2
Division of the University of Michigan College of Engineering; offers comprehensive information technology services and resources to faculty, staff, and students of the College. Includes visual materials documenting people, facilities, and events associated with the organization as well as content produced for its 25th anniversary celebration in 2008.
2.5 linear feet
12.5 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by the University of Michigan Computer Aided Engineering Network (donor no. 10176 ) in 2009.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Computer-Aided Engineering Network (CAEN) is organized as a department reporting to the College of Engineering's Dean's office and is led by the Executive Director of Information Technology. CAEN supplies comprehensive information technology services and resources to faculty, staff, and students of the College of Engineering. In addition to offering computer labs, software, and collaborative work environments, CAEN promotes the use of high performance computing resources in support of teaching and research and provides assistance and consulting to faculty.
CAEN was created in 1983 under the leadership of College Dean James Duderstadt, Associate Dean Daniel Atkins, and its first director, Richard L. Philips (who served until 1986). The original plan called for 400 to 500 personal computer workstations on U-M's Central and North Campuses that would link faculty and students to laboratories, classrooms, offices, and dorms. The initiative was highly innovative at the time and established a model that other institutions would follow in the ensuing decades.
In its first year, CAEN offered 100 Apple Lisa computers for open computing use by all Engineering students in three labs (145 Chrysler Center, 2070 Dow, and the Engineering Library). The following years would see CAEN expand the number and size of labs as well as offer new services for its user community. Telnet services became available in 1988 and the Pine email program entered wide use in 1994, the same year that CAEN and the College appeared on the World Wide Web. 1994 also marked the establishment of Camp CAEN, a "computer exploration camp" that introduced computer science and computer engineering to middle and high school students. During this period, CAEN was led by Randall Frank, who succeeded Philips in 1986 and served until 1995, at which point Paul Killey assumed leadership of the division.
In 1996, the recently completed Integrated Technology Instruction Center (ITIC) was renamed the Media Union (and would later become the Duderstadt Center) and CAEN became one of its first residents. Throughout the late 1990s and early 2000s, CAEN continued to expand its resources and services. Mark Giuffrida was named Director of CAEN in 2001 and as of 2012, the division was jointly led by Giuffrida and Paul Killey, who also serves as Executive Director of Information Technology for the College.
The Computer-Aided Engineering Network (CAEN) records give insight into the evolution of the division's facilities and infrastructure and document the various administrators, staff, and students who have contributed to its success. The materials will be particularly useful to those interested in computing in higher education and as well as in the development of academic IT infrastructure. The CAEN records are comprised of two series: Visual Materials and Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Computer-Aided Engineering Network.; Computers.; Frank, Randy.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Computer-Aided Engineering Network.; Duderstadt Center.; Computers.
Contributors:
Killey, Pul.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Digital files.
- CAEN 25th Anniversary Materials
  The CAEN Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Materials series contains born-digital and digitized content created for the anniversary of the unit's founding in 2008. The series has four main components: signs and placards used to create exhibits; posters used at the 25th anniversary celebration and for an online exhibit; a timeline of important events and innovations over CAEN's first 25 years; and a video of the 25th anniversary exhibits. The placards provide information about hardware and infrastructure employed by CAEN over the years and the posters includes digitized images of photographs in the Visual Materials series. The video documents the exhibit created for CAEN's 25th anniversary and includes footage of various computers and hardware used by the division as well as short introductory pieces by Paul Killey, Mark Giuffrida, and Dan Maleta.
  - Placards and signs 2008
    (Include details about hardware and infrastructure employed by CAEN)
  - Posters 2008
    (Posters created for physical and online exhibits; include digitized versions of images found in the Visual Materials series.)
  - Timeline 2008
    (Documents significant events and achievements over CAEN's existence.)
  - Video 2008
    (Includes a walkthrough of the 25th anniversary exhibit as well as short introductory speeches by Dan Maleta, Mark Giuffrida, and Paul Killey on their experiences and expectations for CAEN.)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains content in various formats that document the people, facilities, infrastructure, and events of CAEN. Video footage includes VHS tapes and a U-Matic tape from the 1980s and 1990s provide a look into CAEN labs and facilities (including a behind-the-scenes tour of the Integrated Technology Instructional Center during its construction), a CAEN/ITD Quiz Bowl during the units 10th anniversary in 1993, and interviews with important administrators about the development of CAEN. A 2005 promotional video gives a thorough overview of Camp CAEN. Photographic materials are comprised of color slides, contact sheets, negatives, and photo albums. Taken together, these materials provide a comprehensive view of CAEN through the late 1990s, with extensive portraits of staff and administrators, images of facilities and hardware, and candid photos of students and personnel at various events. The majority of the photographic materials were taken by CAEN staff member Ann Gordon.
  - Video
    - CAEN buildings and computing sites circa 1985-1990, VHS (Box 1)
    - CAEN Laboratories circa 1985-1995, VHS tape (Box 1)
      (No narration; includes footage of Solid State Electronics and Radiation Laboratories as well as an unidentified facility.)
    - CAEN Quiz Show 1993 (Box 1)
      (Recorded during CAEN 10th Anniversary celebration; features a team representing CAEN against a team from the U-M Information Technology Division with questions about IT systems and computers.)
    - Camp CAEN promotional video 2005
      (Promotional video describing the unique features and course offerings at Camp CAEN, a computer exploration camp for middle and high school students and sponsored by CAEN and the College of Engineering. Narrated by Camp CAEN Director James Todd.)
    - Interior Views of Integrated Technology Instructional Center (ITIC) Building circa 1994, VHS tape (Box 1)
      (Tour of the ITIC--later renamed the Media Union and then Duderstadt Center--with CAEN Director Randy Frank while the building was under construction)
    - Michigan Computer Labs Raw Footage 1989, U-matic Tape (Box 1)
      (Footage of computer lab, perhaps in the Dow Building, with students using computers.)
    - Tribute to Randy Frank circa 1998, VHS tape (Box 1)
      (Details Frank's arrival at U-M and his accomplishments as CAEN director. Includes discussion of CAEN's history, the ITIC Building, and interviews with James Duderstadt, Daniel Atkins, Paul Killey, Bernard Galler, Ken Powell, William Martin, Michael Miller and Barbara O'Keefe.)
  - Photographs
    - General: people, facilities, and events
      (Taken by Ann Gordon with some by Bob Kalmbach; originally maintained in three-ring binders)
      - 1983-1988 (Box 1)
      - 1989 (Box 1)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 1)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
      - 1995-1997 (Box 1)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 2)
      - 2000- (Box 2)
    - Staff Photos
      - CAEN Staff Photos (Box 2)
      - Old Staff Photos (Box 2)
    - Camp CAEN: staff, attendees and events
      (Taken by Ann Gordon; originally maintained in three-ring binders)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - 2002-2006 (Box 2)
  - Slides
    - People, facilities, and events
      - circa 1989 (Box 2)
        (Taken by David Koether and Ann Gordon; one folder originally maintained in three-ring binder)
      - circa 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Contact sheets and negatives
    - 1986-1995 (Box 2)
      (Taken by Ann Gordon; includes materials used in promotional brochures, portraits of staff and administrators, and images of students, equipment, facilities, and events.)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 3)
- Archived Websites
  - 1997-[ONGOING]
    (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)